If you want to master UX design,
you have to start with the fundamentals.
So, let's start from the very beginning.
This is easiest to explain with an example.
Let's say I have three groups of text and icons.
But what if I add a container around both the drinks and the food?
you'll know they're related.
while dessert is not.
Now, what if I only add a container around the drinks?
you'll know it's been selected.
Or you can switch to the actual product.
If I were to change this text to gray,
you'll know it's disabled.
Clicking on it probably won't do anything.
See? How you understood all of that in an instant.
I don't even need to write any instructions.
That's because the UI itself is already communicating all of that.
A great UI is full of these kinds of cues.
For example, the state of a button when it's pressed,
or the highlight and hover states for active items in the navigation bar.
There are even tooltips to show users what the UI can do.
or what it does.
Now, let's take a look at this card.
It's laid out in a clear, logical way,
A repeatable format displays all the information.
But it looks more like a spreadsheet.
and not a piece of design.
So, let's give it some hierarchy.
This is actually pretty intuitive.
We can use size, position, and color to our advantage.
Let's start from the top.
An image always brings with it vivid colors.
and makes browsing a breeze.
Just like how UBER does it.
So, in a situation like this,
The items themselves are the most important thing.
we need to make it big and eye-catching.
And it should be placed at the top.
Otherwise, it'll just get jumbled up with information like the time and date.
And this other information can be placed down below.
And the font size should be much smaller.
And it's this contrast,
For instance, differences in size,
or the difference between elements with color and those without.
This is what actually creates a sense of hierarchy.
And that's why the price should be placed at the top.
and right-aligned.
And we'll make it blue to show that it's different from the other content.
This way, it will catch people's attention.
The location information should be smaller.
and place it at the bottom.
Just like this.
But we don't have to limit ourselves to just the start and end points.
The text can be represented by an icon and a line.
This way, you can show the movement from Jamesville to Syracuse.
without having to state it directly.
Of course, it's not an exact science.
You can absolutely design different styles just like these.
And there's nothing wrong with that.
But the same principles still apply.
Put the most important information at the top.
The larger and more vibrant the content, the more important it is.
And whenever possible, use images.
As you design more and more,
You'll find that when you need labels or buttons,
similar design patterns will emerge.
We'll get into that in a moment.
Now, some people get the wrong idea and think that everything has to be aligned to a 12-column grid.
and the spacing has to be exactly eight pixels.
Take this design, for example. It's not aligned to any of the columns.
And that's perfectly fine.
This is especially true for custom landing pages.
But for pages with a highly consistent structure,
like galleries, blogs, or any page with repeating content.
In fact, grids can be incredibly useful by providing a framework for responsive behavior.
use an eight-column grid on tablets,
and four columns for mobile.
But even more important than overusing grids and layouts is whitespace.
Give your elements room to breathe.
For instance, in a simple block like this one,
The font size and line height for the main heading will look something like this.
while the subheading has its own font size and line height.
And it's the same for buttons.
You can also choose to add a top announcement bar like this one.
Then, just make sure to leave a 32-pixel gap between each element.
But you can also group together elements that naturally belong together.
For instance, an announcement and its text, or body text and its subtext.
And this is actually another way to establish a visual hierarchy.
And this is where we see the four-point grid system really come into play.
All the spacing is a multiple of something.
And it's not just because it looks better.
but because it allows you to always split the spacing in half.
This helps keep the entire design consistent.
Typography is actually a lot of fun.
Because design is mostly text.
And when it comes to choosing a font,
And I can say this with almost absolute certainty:
you don't need more than one typeface for any design.
So, just find a good-looking sans-serif font,
Like the ones you see on screen right now.
And just stick with it.
In my seven years of working in design,
Besides the fonts you see on screen,
I've barely used any other typefaces.
And you shouldn't spend too much time on it either.
To be honest, I'm not a big fan of calling any design skill a 'trick'.
But this method does have a bit of that design feel to it.
It looks okay for now.
But our heading text feels a little too loose.
If you tighten up the letter spacing,
by about 2% to 3%.
and then reduce the line height to around 110% to 120%.
Any large text will instantly look very professional.
However, the hierarchy in typography is a bit more subtle.
If we look back at our previous example,
The font sizes for your text can vary quite a bit.
For landing pages and websites,
Generally, it's not recommended to use more than six different font sizes.
And the range between these six sizes can be quite wide.
But for interfaces like dashboards,
that range will be much smaller.
You usually won't find font sizes larger than 24 pixels.
This is because the information density is higher.
But to be honest,
One of the most important principles in design is to draw inspiration from good sources and conduct research.
Like today's sponsor, MOBAN.
They've handpicked hundreds of thousands of mobile and web apps,
and landing pages.
This way, you can draw inspiration from real-world designs crafted by the world's top design teams anytime you want.
If you're struggling with a specific section,
Just do a quick search,
and instantly find real-world examples.
They even come with links that take you to the actual websites.
If you're interested,
You can access MOBY through the first link down below.
and get a 20% discount.
Alright, let's get back to the video.
Color is tricky to get right.
Plus, everyone has their own preferences.
But personally, I love to start with one primary color.
And this is usually your brand color.
Then, you can brighten it up,
use it as a background color, or darken it for text.
Both of these methods allow you to subtly incorporate nuanced colors.
This makes a design that was once bland much more interesting.
Once you've done all that,
we've actually already built half of our color scale.
And this color hierarchy is precisely how large companies design the states of their color blocks,
charts, and the foundation for all sorts of other elements.
But I also think,
As a beginner,
It's also important to let colors find you.
For example, using a bulletin board to draw attention.
Or, by adding a focus state to an input field.
Or, you could add a green 'new' tag to a link.
These are all examples of semantic colors.
In other words, they have a specific meaning.
Colors that can provide guidance to the user.
Blue represents trust.
Red signifies danger or an emergency.
Yellow represents a warning.
And green represents success.
Always make sure you use color with a purpose.
and not just for decoration.
Now, let's talk about designing in dark mode.
and that brings some very interesting challenges.
First, this card uses a light-colored border.
This makes the contrast a bit too high.
So, we need to tone it down a bit.
In dark mode,
Unlike in light mode, we don't have that drop shadow effect.
So, to create a sense of hierarchy,
We need to make the card a bit brighter than the background.
So, I'll make some adjustments accordingly.
And this tag chip is way too bright.
So, we can just turn down the saturation and brightness.
And we can apply this same principle of contrast to the text.
This creates a sense of hierarchy.
Additionally, dark purple,
Reds and greens also offer a lot of flexibility.
and it's not just limited to navy blue.
blue or gray,
But when it comes to creating a sense of hierarchy,
Shadows are a fantastic tool in light mode.
This shadow, like most others, is just too intense.
So, lowering the opacity and increasing the blur can be a huge help.
The intensity of the shadow you need depends on the foreground and background.
But for card-like elements, you'll want a much softer shadow.
But for elements like pop-ups, which sit on top of other content,
will require a stronger shadow.
This creates effects like raised, tactile buttons.
Just remember,
If the shadow is the first thing you notice in a design,
that means you're doing it wrong.
So, to create a powerful design,
You're also going to need icons.
The problem is, most icons are usually way too big.
So, the trick is to get your font's line height.
So, for example, let's say this is 24 pixels.
Then, make the icon the same height as the line height.
Then, tighten up the spacing between the text.
Take these sidebar links, for instance.
Basically, it's a button with no background.
and the background only appears when you hover over it.
This type of button is often called a ghost button.
Now, if we take one of these and isolate it,
and center it.
And you get a perfect, standalone button.
Now, when you have a primary and a secondary call-to-action button appearing side-by-side,
This is a very common design pattern.
Now, about the padding for these buttons.
These buttons can also have icons or be icon-less.
A good design principle is that whenever a user performs any action,
the interface should provide corresponding feedback.
For example, every button should have at least four states.
Default, hover,
activated or pressed, and disabled.
Sometimes, you'll also need a loading state.
And when you pair that with a loading animation, the feedback for the input field becomes even more critical.
When a user clicks on an input field, it needs to have a focused state.
If an error occurs, it should be marked with a red border and an error message.
Sometimes, you also need to add a warning state for optional questions.
And this applies everywhere.
For instance, show a loading animation while data is being loaded.
or a success message once an action is completed.
You can even add subtle animations when scrolling or swiping.
Every interaction needs a feedback.
And this naturally brings us to the topic of micro-interactions.
Micro-interactions are a form of feedback.
But they can significantly enhance the experience.
But we still don't know if it was actually copied successfully.
But what if, instead, we have this notification bar slide in?
This is a microinteraction that confirms our action.
These micro-interactions can be incredibly practical.
They can also be fun and playful.
Finally, overlays are incredibly important.
Because if you don't handle it properly,
Not only will the image be ruined,
but the text will suffer as well.
So, in a situation like this,
But we can't just leave it like this.
But either way,
We could add a full-screen overlay.
But that approach doesn't really do justice to the beauty of the image.
So, let's try a different approach and add a linear gradient instead.
This way, we can still showcase the image,
while also creating a smooth transition to a background that's easier to read text on.
Or, if we want to make it a bit more flashy,
You can also layer a progressive blur on top of the gradient.
to give the whole thing a more modern look.
And that pretty much covers all the fundamental UI/UX concepts.
And we've covered it all in just 10 minutes.
If you want to learn more about MOBBY,
You can click the first link down below.
You can also get the links to all the FIGMA resources used in this video.
Those links are down below as well.
Thank you so much for watching.
See you in the next one.